<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bloody nevves from Norvvich or, a true relation of a bloody attempt of the papists in Norwich, to consume the whole city by fire. VVhich they had begun to put in practice setting a house a fire, at the lower end of High-Bridge-street, burning it to the ground, but by Gods mercy, they were hindered from doing any more mischiefe. Likewise here is added the last bloody newes from Ireland. Consisting of a bloody tragedy acted upon the body of the Lord Coffeld a Protestant, conspired by Sir Philip Moneale a trecherous and bloody rebell, with the like cruelty done to Mr. Ironmonger, by the rebels, also after what manner he being slaine, they committed his father to prison, and threw his wife and children out of doores naked. VVith the relation of how many vvagons went out of London, laden vvith ammunition to be conveigh'd to Ireland, for the use of our distressed brethren, the Protestants the 2. of Decemb.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E179_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6365</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872976</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872976</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125423</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125423)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 31:E179[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bloody nevves from Norvvich or, a true relation of a bloody attempt of the papists in Norwich, to consume the whole city by fire. VVhich they had begun to put in practice setting a house a fire, at the lower end of High-Bridge-street, burning it to the ground, but by Gods mercy, they were hindered from doing any more mischiefe. Likewise here is added the last bloody newes from Ireland. Consisting of a bloody tragedy acted upon the body of the Lord Coffeld a Protestant, conspired by Sir Philip Moneale a trecherous and bloody rebell, with the like cruelty done to Mr. Ironmonger, by the rebels, also after what manner he being slaine, they committed his father to prison, and threw his wife and children out of doores naked. VVith the relation of how many vvagons went out of London, laden vvith ammunition to be conveigh'd to Ireland, for the use of our distressed brethren, the Protestants the 2. of Decemb.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p., 1 leaf of plate : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Greensmith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charlemont, Toby Caulfeild, --  Baron, 1621-1642.</term>
               <term>O'Neill, Phelim, --  Sir, 1604?-1653.</term>
               <term>Walker, Henry, --  Ironmonger.</term>
               <term>Insurgency --  England --  Norwich --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:125423:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125423:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BLOODY NEWES FROM NORWICH: OR, A True Relation of a bloody attempt of the Papiſts in <hi>Norwich,</hi> to conſume the whole City by fire.</p>
            <p>VVhich they had begun to put in practice ſetting a houſe a fire, at the lower end of High-Bridge-ſtreet, burning it to the ground, but by Gods mercy, they were hindered from doing any more miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe here is added the laſt bloody Newes from <hi>Jreland.</hi> Conſiſting of a bloody Tragedy acted upon the body of the Lord <hi>Coffeld</hi> a Proteſtant, conſpired by Sir <hi>Philip Moneale</hi> a Trecherous and bloody Rebell, With the like cruelty done to Mr. <hi>Jronmonger,</hi> by the Rebels, alſo after what manner he being ſlaine, they committed his Father to priſon, and threw his wife and children out of doores naked.</p>
            <p>VVith the Relation of how many VVa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons went out of <hi>London,</hi> laden with ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be conveigh'd to <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the uſe of our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Brethren, the Proteſtants the 2. of <hi>Decemb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Iohn Greenſmith.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:125423:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125423:2"/>
            <head>News from <hi>Nerwich.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ill mourning never ceaſe, nor lamentation have an end? Will Trechery ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be exiled this Land, but ſtill haue its harbor here: O yee blood thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Papiſts, what are your intents? Doe you thinke that there is not a juſt God above, who doth ſee and behold all your wicked deſignes? Have you bin foſtered up in this Nation as Aeſops Ploughman did the Sneake which he redeemed from the oppreſſion of the cold to deſtroy us? How often hath God repelled the force of your wicked machinations and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Plots and yet will you take no warning? Doe you thinke becauſe you eſcape puniſhment for a time that God will ſuffer you for ever? No no aſſure your ſelves that Jehovah is juſt? Doe not you duely read your wicked enterpriſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the common view of the whole world, and yet will you daily encreaſe your miſchievous Plots, one of which I am to declare intended for the deſtruction of <hi>Norwichs</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:125423:3"/>
            <p>Vpon the 17. day of Novemb. 1641, was there a great uproare in <hi>Norwich</hi> concurning the Papiſts ariſing there, they being intended to burne the whole City without any remorſe, two being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed privily for the ſame purpoſe, one to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at one end of the City, and the ſecond at the other end, the one was diſcovered being about to ſet fire to a tharcht houſe, the other he ſet the houſe on fire joyning to High Bridge ſtreet, which was burnt to the ground, to the great aſſoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole City, but now there, is ſtrong watching and warding in every corner of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to prevent further danger.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>From <hi>Ireland</hi> the 25. of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO what a miſerable height of wickedneſſe is this world growne too, when one friend ſhall not know how to truſt the other, as ſhall now by this enſuing bloody Story be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Coffeld</hi> and Sir <hi>Philip Moneale</hi> being very intimate &amp; familiar friends, were wont con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly once in two weekes to viſit each other, my Lord comming to his houſe with ſome 6. men at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on him, and ſo likewiſe, Sir <hi>Pilip</hi> with the ſame attendance, my Lord having bin at the houſe of Sir <hi>Philip,</hi> deſired Sir <hi>Philip</hi> to come upon a time appointed unto him, within a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night St <hi>Philip</hi> according to his promiſe, came to viſite Lord <hi>Cofeld</hi> but it proved a very bloody vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation,
<pb facs="tcp:125423:3"/>yet not-with handing they ſecond all to be very metry and frolicke at the firſt, but Sr. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> would alwayes be looking out of the window into the yard, whereupon the Lord <hi>Coffeld</hi> called to Sir Philip to come unto the fire becauſe it was cold, but Sir Philip had a ſecret fire burning in his breaſt which warmed him, wherefore fire ſtill continued looking out of the window, where hee perceived men ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in to the Lord <hi>Coffelds</hi> houſe, by ſeverall numbers, ſometime fowre at a time, othertimes 6 or 7, till they came to the number of about three hundred, but as they came they went in at a backe doore, which St. <hi>Philip Moneale</hi> perceiving, he ſpako to the Lord <hi>Coffeld</hi> ſaying, now my Lord you are my Priſoner, but he taking it as a jeſt, ſpoke merrily: nay Sr. <hi>Philip</hi> you are my Priſoner, meaning becauſe he was in his Lordſhips houſe at that preſent, upon which words Sr <hi>Philip</hi> had the doores opened, then entred in the Rebels and ſeized upon the Lord <hi>Cofields</hi> perſon, diſmounting his Ordinance from his houſe top, and afterward ſlew him, and pillaged his houſe.</p>
            <p>O yuheard of treachery againſt ſo loving a friend, but <hi>J</hi> muſt not ſtand in admiration of this becauſe I have as bloody to relate.</p>
            <p>The Rebels hearts in Jreland are ſet upon nothing but miſchiefs, and bloody villany, came into the houſe
<pb facs="tcp:125423:4"/>of Mr. <hi>Jronmonger,</hi> and acted ſuch a Tragedy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould the bloody Chronicle wherin is regiſtred all the inhumane acts whichever were done be ſearcht, this act of theirs is not to be paraleld. Which was thus.</p>
            <p>They (the Rebels I meane) entring into the houſe, ſeazed upon the old man Mr. Jremongers father, and haled him out of the houſe to priſon.</p>
            <p>Then did they drag the man himſelfe, from the fide of his tender wife, and children, and threw him upon the table, where before his wifes face with a hatchet, in a moſt Lamentable manner, cut off his head, and then with the ſame harchet did they mangle his quarters, which being done, they rance upon his wife, and children, and naked as they were, threw them out of doores.</p>
            <p>Thus doe theſe bloody minded Rebels, dayly act their villany, by perſecuting and murthering the poore Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>But now by the helpe of God, we doe not feare but their forces ſhall be over throwne, and their villanies have a period, inſomuch as upon Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day being the ſecond of <hi>Decemb.</hi> there went out of <hi>London,</hi> above forty wagons laden with Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Match, and Bullets, which are to be conveigh'd to Weſtcheſter, and ſo by ſhip to be tranſported to Ireland, to arme thoſe poore oppreſſed Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants which ſtand in need of them.</p>
            <p>O God of thy great mercy comfort them ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leaſt their Enemies boaſt, and ſay, where is now now their God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:125423:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>O hone, O hone.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
